Register of the the Isaac Leon Kandel Papers, 1915-1966
Hoover Institution Archives
Isaac Leon Kandel Papers,
1915-1966
84032
Kandel, I. L. (Isaac Leon), 1881-1965
9 manuscript boxes (3.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Contains correspondence, writings and background materials relating to international education and Kandel's career as a leading comparative and international educator
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984 with an additional increment in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1881 Born, Romania
1905 M.A., University of Manchester, United Kingdom
1907 Travelled to Germany to study with the Herbartian educational theorist Wilhelm Rein at the University of Jena
1908 Moved to the U.S., New York
1909-1913 Lecturer at the Teachers' College, Columbia University Assistant editor of Cyclopedia of Education
1910 PhD, Teachers College, Columbia University, dissertation titled: "The Training of Elementary School Teachers in Germany"
1914-1923 Researcher, Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching
1923-1946 Chair, History of Education, Teachers College, Columbia University
1924-1944 Editor of Educational Yearbook
1930 Author, History of Secondary Education
1933 Author, Comparative Education
1935 Author, The Making of Nazis
1937 Awarded a Doctor of Letters degree by University of Melbourne, Australia and the Legion of Honor Chevalier (Knight) by the French government
1937-1946 Member of the United States National Committee on Intellectual Cooperation
1938 Author, Conflicting Theories of Education
1946 Awarded a Doctor of Laws degree by the University of North Carolina
1946-1953 Editor, School and Society
1946-1962 Writer, editor and consultant for the United Nations and UNESCO
1946 Part of the United States educational mission to Japan
1948 Author, Education in an Era of Transition
1948-1950 First professor of American Studies at Manchester University
1951 Author, Raising the School-leaving Age, series of six books issued by UNESCO
1955 Author, The New Era in Education: a Comparative Study
1965 Died in Geneva, Switzerland
Scope and Content of Collection
Contains correspondence, writings and background materials relating to international education and Kandel's career as a leading comparative and international educator.
The Biographical file and Correspondence series document Kandels work as a Professor and the chair of History of Education at the Teachers' College, Columbia University, a researcher for the Carnegie Foundation, an editor of School and Society and Educational Yearbook, as well as a writer, editor andConsultant for the United Nations and UNESCO. The Writings series provides further details of Kandel's contributions to the general field of education and to the specialized field of comparative and international education.
Access Points
Education.; International education.
Container List
- Biographical file, 1927-1966 (Box 1)
  Includes appointments, invitation and awards, memoirs, and a series of oral history interviews. Also includes photographic portraits of Isaac Kandel
  - Appointments, invitations, and awards, 1927-1954 (Folder 1: 1)
  - The Reminiscences of Isaac L. Kandel, Oral History Research Office, Columbia University, 1962 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Isaac Leon Kandel (1881-1965): A Biographical Memoir by Lawrence A Cremin, National Academy of Education, 1966 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Photographs depicting Isaac Kandel and others (16 prints), circa 1940 (Folder 1: 4)
- Correspondence, 1919-1966 (Box 1)
  Contains incoming and outgoing correspondence primarily relating to his career as a writer and educator. Correspondence organized alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - A-W, 1919-1962 (Folder 1: 5-6)
  - Bereday, George, 1955-1966 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Carnegie Foundation, 1952-1953 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Houghton Mifflin Company, 1955-1960 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Kappa Delta Pi, 1957-1958 (Folder 1: 10)
  - I Problemi Della Pedagogia, 1956 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Library of Congress, 1954 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Minowa, Saburo, 1950-1952 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Sadler, Michael, 1936-1937 (Folder 1: 14)
  - UNESCO, 1948-1951 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Universities, 1947-1960 (Folder 1)
    - A-W, 1934-1960 (Folder 1: 16)
    - Columbia, 1937-1954 (Folder 1: 17)
    - Harvard, 1957-1960 (Folder 1: 18)
    - London, 1933-1948 (Folder 1: 19)
    - Manchester, 1948-1953 (Folder 1: 20)
    - Oxford, 1949-1950 (Folder 1: 21)
    - Yale, 1945-1947 (Folder 1: 22)
- Writings, 1900-1965 (Box 2-9)
  Includes articles, speeches, book reviews, drafts and notes written by Kandel as well as material related to the articles, including correspondence, collected research and articles, and clippings. Additional materials included with an article may have a larger date range than the publication year. Writings organized by the creator alphabetically by title or subject.
  - "Academic Freedom for Teachers," Teachers College Review, Vol. 37, No. 3, 1935 (Folder 2: 1)
  - "Achievements in Education of American Democracy,", 1900-1939 (Folder 2: 2)
  - "Administration of Education in England and Wales," Current History, 1933-1958 (Folder 2: 3)
  - "Adult Education and the Future of Democracy," The Educational Forum, 1944 (Folder 2: 4)
  - "Alice in Cloud-Cuckoo-Land," The Teachers College Record, 1933 (Folder 2: 5)
  - "American and English Education Compared," The Educational Forum, 1948 (Folder 2: 6)
  - American education, 1951-1960 (Folder 2: 9-Jul)
  - "American Philosophy of Education," The University of London, Institute of Education, Review of Educational Thought, Evans Brothers Ltd., 1935-1937 (Folder 2: 10)
  - "The American University in American Social Life," The Educational Forum, 1938-1983 (Folder 2: 11)
  - "Backgrounds for Education," Schoolmen's Week, 1936-1959 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Book reviews, 1923-1960 (Folder 2: 13)
  - "Challenge of World Responsibilities," School and Society, 1953 (Folder 2: 14)
  - "Challenge to Democracy," School Management, 1936 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Chapel addresses, 1940-1941 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Comparative education, 1926-1961 (Folder 2: 17-19)
  - Comprehensive schools, 1930-1951 (Folder 3: 1)
  - "Conclusions and Recommendations of the Social Studies Commission of the American Historical Association,"Educational Administration and Supervisor, 1935 (Folder 3: 2)
  - "Controversy Ended," The Educational Forum, 1958 (Folder 3: 3)
  - "Crisis de la educación," Educación y Cultura, Año 1, Núm 6, México, 1940 (Folder 3: 4)
  - "Cult of Uncertainty," Jesuit Educational Quarterly, 1944 (Folder 3: 5)
  - "Cultivating the Love of Learning,", circa 1930 (Folder 3: 6)
  - "Current Thinking in Education - The Unrest in Education," New York State Education, 1940 (Folder 3: 7)
  - "Danger of Complacency," School and Society, Vol. 76, No. 1981, 1952 (Folder 3: 8)
  - "Degree and Teaching,", 1939 (Folder 3: 9)
  - "Der Amerikanische Geist in der Briehung,"Padagogisches Zentralblatt, Sonderdruck aus Heft 9, Verlag Julius Beltz, Langensalza, 1928 (Folder 3: 10)
  - "Development of American Spiritual Life," address delivered at the Jewish Theological Seminary, 1939 (Folder 3: 11)
  - "Discipline,", 1941 (Folder 3: 12)
  - "Education,", 1955 (Folder 3: 13-14)
  - Education abroad, 1918-1960 (Folder 3: 15-16)
  - "Education and Democracy,", 1900-1939 (Folder 3: 17-18)
  - "Education and National Defense," The Educational Forum, 1940 (Folder 3: 19)
  - "Education and Peace," School and Society, Vol. 56, No. 1442, 1942-1948 (Folder 3: 20)
  - "Education and Politics" The Kadelpian Review, Vol. 14, No. 2, 1935-1943 (Folder 3: 21)
  - "Education and Social Change," Journal of Social Philosophy, Vol. 1, No. 1, 1931-1944 (Folder 3: 22)
  - "Education and Social Disorder," Teachers College Record, Vol. 34, No. 5, 1933 (Folder 3: 23)
  - "Education and Social Forces," The Educational Forum, Vol. 14, No. 1, 1949 (Folder 3: 24)
  - "Education and Statesmanship," International Review of Education, Vol. 4, No. 1, 1958 (Folder 3: 25)
  - "Education in a Changing World," School and Society, Vol. 43, No. 1122, 1936 (Folder 3: 26)
  - "Education in Europe-Outlook and Tendencies," Teachers College Record, Vol. 26, No. 9, 1918-1935 (Folder 3: 27-28)
  - "Education in Latin America," address delivered in the Latin American Lecture Series of the Institute of Latin American Studies, The University of Texas, 1947 (Folder 4: 1)
  - "Education in Transition,", circa 1944 (Folder 4: 2)
  - "Education Today," Understanding Through Education, 1946 (Folder 4: 3)
  - "Education: A Bridge for Cultural Understanding," The Educational Forum, 1945 (Folder 4: 4)
  - "Education: Which Kind for Your Child? As Essentialists Would Have It," The Parents Magazine, 1938 (Folder 4: 5)
  - "Educational Problems"The American Scholar Forum, Vol. 14, No. 4, 1920-1958 (Folder 4: 6)
  - "Educational Tendencies in Germany and England," School and Society Vol. 4, No. 79, 1916 and Vol. 5, No. 127, 1917 (Folder 4: 7)
  - "El Final de una polemica," La Educación, Año 3, 1958 (Folder 4: 8)
  - "Elite or Leaders?" School and Society, 1956 (Folder 4: 9)
  - "English-Speaking World in the War and the Peace," Teachers College Record, Vol. 43, No. 3, 1942 (Folder 4: 10)
  - "Equality of Educational Opportunity and Its Problem," International Pädagogische Kontakte, 1963 (Folder 4: 11)
  - "Estados Unidos, Serie dirigida por I. L. Kandel," Número 3-7, American Council on Education, Washington, D.C., 1943-1945 (Folder 4: 12-13)
  - "Fantasia of Current Education," The American Scholar, Vol. 10, No. 3, 1941 (Folder 4: 14)
  - "Federal Aid for Research and Training in the Humanities,", circa 1950 (Folder 4: 15)
  - "Federal Aid to Education," The New Republic, 1918 (Folder 4: 16)
  - "Federal Participation in Education,", 1961 (Folder 4: 17)
  - "Free Library Movement and Its Implications," The Free Library Movement, Sydney, 1937 (Folder 4: 18)
  - "Freedom and Bias in Education," The Kadelpian Review, Vol. 15, No. 1, 1935 (Folder 4: 19)
  - "General Education,", circa 1950 (Folder 4: 20)
  - "General Ideas on the Teaching of History, Geography, etc,", circa 1930 (Folder 4: 21)
  - "Het Doel Het Amerikaansche Onderwijs," Paedagogische Studiën, circa 1950 (Folder 4: 22)
  - "History of the Curriculum," Experimental Edition, 1935 (Folder 4: 23)
  - History of examinations, 1937-1953 (Folder 4: 24-25)
  - "Hitler Is the Law," The National School, Vol. 17, No. 1, 1936 (Folder 5: 1)
  - "Home and Education," Women's League Outlook, 1932 (Folder 5: 2)
  - "How Old Is the New Social Order Movement?" Teachers College Record, 1934 (Folder 5: 3)
  - "In the Memory of Paul Klapper,", 1952 (Folder 5: 4)
  - "Intellectual Freedom," Teachers College Record, Vol. 43, No. 5, 1942 (Folder 5: 5)
  - "International Concern for Education," American Review, 1924 (Folder 5: 6)
  - "International Cooperation in Education," The Educational Forum, 1942 (Folder 5: 7)
  - "International Institute of Teachers College," Teachers College Record, Vol. 24, No. 4, 1923 (Folder 5: 8)
  - "Internationalism Begins at Home," The Educational Forum, Vol. 9, No. 1, 1944 (Folder 5: 9)
  - "Internationalism of Scholarship and Learning," Eighth Conference on Science, Philosophy and Religion, 1947 (Folder 5: 10)
  - "Introduzione," La Scuola negli Stati Uniti, Parte I, Primo Supplemento Speciale del Bullettino di Educazione Publicato Dall'USIS, Ufficio Informazioni Stati Uniti, 1946 (Folder 5: 11)
  - "Is the New Education Progressive?" Educational Administration and Supervision, Vol. 22, No. 8, 1936 (Folder 5: 12)
  - "Is the Scrutiny of Educational Materials a Police Measure?", 1945 (Folder 5: 13)
  - Jewish education, 1930-1942 (Folder 5: 14)
  - "Junior High School in European Systems," The Educational Review, Vol. 58, No. 4, 1919 (Folder 5: 15)
  - "Knowledge and Wisdom,", circa 1950 (Folder 5: 16)
  - "Language and Human Values,", 1943 (Folder 5: 17)
  - "Leadership and Education in Other Times and in Other Lands," Teachers College Record, Vol. 40, No. 7 Includes "Address Delivered Before the Fifth Conference on Education Politics, 1938 November 12, Advanced School of Education, Teachers College, Columbia University, 1939 (Folder 5: 18)
  - Liberal education, 1932-1956 (Folder 5: 19)
  - "Liberal Education and Quality," The Educational Forum, 1961 (Folder 5: 20)
  - "Liberal Education and Technology," address delivered before Nu Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa, Hunter College of the City of New York, 1945 (Folder 5: 21)
  - "Liberalism and Education" The Educational Forum, 1937-1961 (Folder 5: 22)
  - "Living Comenius," The American-Czechoslovak Fellowship, Vol. 1, No. 1, 1942 (Folder 5: 23)
  - "Looking Forward," The Educational Forum, 1945 (Folder 5: 24)
  - "Making of Citizens in England," Teachers College Record, 1928 (Folder 5: 25)
  - "Mid-European Studies Center,", 1950-1953 (Folder 5: 26)
  - "Mobilizing the Teacher," The Teachers College Record, 1934, 1932-1945 (Folder 6: 1)
  - "Modern Issues in Education," address at the American University at Cairo, 1938 (Folder 6: 2)
  - National and international aspects of education, 1946-1956 (Folder 6: 3-4)
  - "Nationalism,", circa 1940 (Folder 6: 5)
  - Nationalism and education, 1934-1941 (Folder 6: 6)
  - "New School," Teachers College Record, Vol. 18, No. 6, 1932 (Folder 6: 7)
  - "Obligations of the Educated Person," School and Society, Vol. 64, No. 1651, 1946 (Folder 6: 8)
  - "Origin of Normal Schools in the United States,", circa 1930 (Folder 6: 9)
  - "Our Adolescent Education,"Educational Administration and Supervision, Vol. 18, No. 8, 1932-1961 (Folder 6: 10)
  - "Outlook in Education," Institute of Education, University of London, Studies and Reports, No. 2, Oxford University Press, 1933 (Folder 6: 11)
  - "Ph.D. Degree," The Journal of High Education, Vol. 10, No. 5, 1939 (Folder 6: 12)
  - "Philosophy of Education," The Harvard Educational Review, Vol. 26, No. 2, 1956 (Folder 6: 13)
  - "Political Theory and Education," reprinted from Teachers College Record, 1916 (Folder 6: 14)
  - "Prejudice the Garden Toward Roses?" The American Scholar, Vol. 8, No. 1, 1938 (Folder 6: 15)
  - "Principles of Educational Administration,"National Conference of Education, 1960 (Folder 6: 16)
  - "Professional Training of Teachers," The Educational Times, 1921 (Folder 6: 17)
  - "Prussian Schools," The New Republic, 1918 (Folder 6: 18)
  - "Public and the Schools,", 1942 (Folder 6: 19)
  - "Raising the School-Leaving Age," Studies on Compulsory Education, UNESCO, 1951 (Folder 6: 20)
  - "Rediscovery of America," Percival lecture at University of Manchester, 1950 (Folder 6: 21)
  - "Report on Secondary Education in Jamaica," The Gleaner Co., Ltd., Kingston, JA, 1941 (Folder 6: 22)
  - "Revolution and Evolution,", circa 1950 (Folder 6: 23)
  - "Scholarship and Research," The Educational Forum, Vol. 19, No. 3, 1955 (Folder 6: 24)
  - Secondary education, 1930-1961 (Folder 7: 1-5)
  - "Sentimentalism or Understanding?" The Educational Forum, 1941 (Folder 7: 6)
  - "Significance of Foreign Experience in the Preparation of Teachers,", circa 1950 (Folder 7: 7)
  - "Social Background,", circa 1945 (Folder 7: 8)
  - "Society - the Chief Examiner," The College Board Review, No. 21, 1953 (Folder 7: 9)
  - "Some Educational Paradoxes," The Educational Forum, Vol. 22, No. 3, 1958 (Folder 7: 10)
  - "Soviet Challenge and Secondary Education in the United States," The Educational Forum, 1956 (Folder 7: 11)
  - "Spencer's Place in Education Not Assured Until Recently" The Evening Post, New York (Folder 7: 12)
  - State and education, 1920-1952 (Folder 7: 13)
  - "State's Right to Certify Teachers," New York State Education, 1938 (Folder 7: 14)
  - "Study of Foreign Languages in the Present Crisis," paper read at a meeting of the Foreign Language Teachers' Conference, Lincoln School Auditorium, N.Y.C., 1942 (Folder 7: 15)
  - "Teorie filosofische dell'educazione americana," Istituto di Pedagogia dell 'Universita' di Roma, 1956 (Folder 7: 16)
  - "Textbook and Revolutions," The Educational Forum, Vol. 18, No. 2, 1954 (Folder 7: 17)
  - "Training of Elementary School Teachers in Mathematics," United States Bureau of Education, 1915 (Folder 7: 18)
  - "Transmission of Culture: Education as an Instrument of National Policy," Seventh Conference on Science, Philosophy and Religion, 1940 (Folder 7: 19)
  - U. S. Education Mission to Japan, 1946-1950 (Folder 7: 20)
  - "UNESCO,", circa 1950 (Folder 7: 21)
  - University developments and its problem, 1939-1951 (Folder 7: 22)
  - "University Study of Education," Chapter II, circa 1950 (Folder 7: 23)
  - "Varied and Attractive Programme," address at North of England Education Conference, 1948 (Folder 7: 24)
  - "We Move Toward Centralization," The National School, Vol. 18, No. 2, 1935 (Folder 7: 25)
  - "What Is College For?" American Review, 1923 (Folder 7: 26)
  - "What Is a Liberal Education?" The Educational Forum, 1942 (Folder 8: 1)
  - "What We May Learn from Other Countries," American Council on Education Studies, Religion and Public Education, 1945 (Folder 8: 2)
  - "Where Propaganda Begins," The National School, Vol. 18, No. 3, 1936 (Folder 8: 3)
  - "William Chandler Bagley: Stalwart Educator,"Educational Forum, 1939-1961 (Folder 8: 4)
  - Year Book of Education, 1925-1965 (Folder 8: 5-6)
  - Background material, 1918-1960 (Folder 8)
    - Notes, quotations, collected articles and drafts, 1920-1960 (Folder 8: 7-17)
    - The Times: Educational Supplement, London, August-December 1918, June, October 1919 (Folder 9: 1-4)